Finding Aid for Rick Haynes Michigan Militia collection, 1993-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rick Haynes Michigan Militia collection 1993-1999
Haynes, Rick
1 linear foot
0440 Aa 2
Collection of photocopies of records, publications, and materials of and about Michigan civilian militia organization; with a number of publications produced by civilian militias outside of the state of Michigan. Materials were originally collected by Rick Haynes, who at different times served as Information Officer and the 8th Division Michigan Militia Corps Wolverines Divisional Officer.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection was donated by Jo Ellen Vinyard (donor no. 7735 ) in 2000.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Rick Haynes has been with the Michigan Militia since it was founded in 1994 by Norm Olson, a pastor and gun shop owner, and a former U.S. Air Force Non-Commissioned Officer. Haynes served as Information Officer for over 2 years and later became the Divisional Officer for the 8th Division Michigan Militia Corps Wolverines. Haynes has continuously worked with several militia administration leaders, including Norm Olson, Lynn Van Huzien, Tom Wayne, Joe Pilchack, among others.
The Rick Haynes collection consists of photocopies of correspondence, newsletters, and other collected information detailing activities and ideology of the Michigan Militia.
Subjects:
Haynes, Rick.; Militia movements--Michigan.; Michigan Militia Corps.; Right-wing extremists--Michigan.
- Records
  The Records series includes indexes and contents of materials that were originally placed in two 3-ring binders called "Book O" and "Book W" (at present the meaning of titles of these books is not clear). The Books contain correspondence, memoranda, and various materials distributed among member of the Michigan militia.
  - Book O index (Box 1)
  - Book O, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Book W index (Box 1)
  - Book W, 6 folders (Box 1)
- Topical files
  The Topical files series contains collected materials on various topics, information about events and meetings, training manuals, and miscellaneous material.
  - 4th Brigade, 8th Division (Box 1)
  - Events, 1995-1999 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Federal government (Box 1)
  - Military and police force (Box 1)
  - Militias (Box 1)
  - Narcotics (Box 1)
  - Norman Olson (Box 1)
  - Oklahoma City bombing (Box 1)
  - Petition de Droit, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Public health issues (Box 1)
  - Technology (Box 1)
  - Training (Box 1)
  - United Nations and international issues (Box 1)
  - U.S. laws and legislation (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publications series contains newsletters published by Michigan militia and militia organizations from other states, as well as articles and research material about Michigan militia and the militia movement in the U.S.
  - Relevance, 1994-1995 (scattered), 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Weekly Update, August 1995-October 1996, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - News Room, 1997 (scattered), February 1999 (Box 1)
  - Weekly News, October 1998-April 1999, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan militia miscellaneous publications, 1995-[1996 ?] (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous militia publications from outside of state of Michigan, 1994-1996, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan militia Web site (Box 1)
  - Research materials about Michigan Militia, 4 folders (Box 1)